<chapter  id="coordinate-system">
  <title>
    Coordinate Systems
  </title>
  <para>
    A variable's spatiotemporal dimensions are used to locate data values in
    time and space. This is accomplished by associating these dimensions with
    the relevant set of latitude, longitude, vertical, and time coordinates.
    This section presents two methods for making that association: the use of
    <emphasis>coordinate variables</emphasis>, and the use of 
    <emphasis>auxiliary coordinate variables</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>
    All of a variable's dimensions that are latitude, longitude, vertical,
    or time dimensions (see <xref linkend="terminology"/>) must have
    corresponding coordinate variables, i.e., one-dimensional variables
    with the same name as the dimension (see examples
    in <xref linkend="coordinate-types"/>). This is the only method of
    associating dimensions with coordinates that is supported
    by <biblioref linkend="coards">COARDS</biblioref>.
  </para>
  <para>
    All of a variable's spatiotemporal dimensions that are not latitude,
    longitude, vertical, or time dimensions are required to be associated
    with the relevant latitude, longitude, vertical, or time coordinates
    via the new <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute of the variable.
    The value of the <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute is
    <emphasis>a blank separated list of the names of auxiliary coordinate variables</emphasis>.
    There is no restriction on the order in which the auxiliary coordinate
    variables appear in the <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute string.
    <emphasis role="deletedtext">
    The dimensions of an auxiliary coordinate variable must be a subset of
    the dimensions of the variable with which the coordinate is associated
    (an exception is label coordinates (<xref linkend="labels"/>) which
    contain a dimension for maximum string length).</emphasis>
    <emphasis role="newtext">
    The dimensions of an auxiliary coordinate variable must be a subset of the
    dimensions of the variable with which the coordinate is associated, with
    two exceptions. First, string-valued coordinates (<xref linkend="labels"/>)
    have a dimension for maximum string length. Second, in the ragged array
    representations of data (<xref linkend="discrete-sampling-geometries"/>),
    special methods are needed to connect the data and coordinates
    </emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
    We recommend that the
    name of a multidimensional coordinate variable should not match the name
    of any of its dimensions because that precludes supplying a
    coordinate variable for the dimension. This practice also avoids potential
    bugs in applications that determine coordinate variables by only checking
    for a name match between a dimension and a variable and not checking that
    the variable is one dimensional.
  </para>
  <para>
    The use of coordinate variables is required whenever they are applicable.
    That is, auxiliary coordinate variables may not be used as the only way
    to identify latitude and longitude coordinates that could be identified
    using coordinate variables. This is both to enhance conformance to COARDS
    and to facilitate the use of generic applications that recognize the NUG
    convention for coordinate variables. An application that is trying to
    find the latitude coordinate of a variable should always look first to
    see if any of the variable's dimensions correspond to a latitude
    coordinate variable. If the latitude coordinate is not found this way,
    then the auxiliary coordinate variables listed by the
    <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute should be checked. Note that it
    is permissible, but optional, to list coordinate variables as well as
    auxiliary coordinate variables in the <varname>coordinates</varname>
    attribute.
    </para>
    <para>
    If an <varname>axis</varname> attribute is attached to an auxiliary coordinate variable, it can
    be used by applications in the same way the <varname>axis</varname> attribute attached to a
    coordinate variable is used. However, it is not permissible for a data variable to have both a
    coordinate variable and an auxiliary coordinate variable, or more than one of either type of
    variable, having an <varname>axis</varname> attribute with any given value e.g. there must be no
    more than one <varname>axis</varname> attribute for <varname>X</varname> for any data
    variable. Note that if the <varname>axis</varname> attribute is not specified for an auxiliary
    coordinate variable, it may still be possible to determine if it is a spatiotemporal dimension
    from its own units or standard_name, or from the units and standard_name of the coordinate
    variable corresponding to its dimensions (see <xref linkend="coordinate-types"/> ). For
    instance, auxiliary coordinate variables which lie on the horizontal surface can be identified
    as such by their dimensions being horizontal. Horizontal dimensions are those whose coordinate
    variables have an <varname>axis</varname> attribute of <varname>X</varname> or
    <varname>Y</varname>, or a <varname>units</varname> attribute indicating latitude and longitude.
  </para>
  <para>
    If the coordinate variables for a horizontal grid are not longitude
    and latitude, it is recommended that they be supplied
    <emphasis>in addition</emphasis> to the required coordinates.
    For example, the Cartesian coordinates of a map projection should be
    supplied as coordinate variables in addition to the required
    two-dimensional latitude and longitude variables that are identified
    via the <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute.
    The use of the <varname>axis</varname> attribute with
    values <varname>X</varname> and <varname>Y</varname> is recommended
    for the coordinate variables(see <xref linkend="coordinate-types"/>).
  </para>
  <para>
    It is sometimes not practical to specify the latitude-longitude
    location of data which is representative of geographic regions
    with complex boundaries. For this purpose, provision is made
    in <xref linkend="geographic-regions"/> for indicating the region
    by a standardized name.
  </para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Independent Latitude, Longitude, Vertical, and Time Axes</title>
    <para>
      When each of a variable's spatiotemporal dimensions is a latitude,
      longitude, vertical, or time dimension, then each axis is
      identified by a coordinate variable.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Independent coordinate variables</title>
      <programlisting>
dimensions:
  lat = 18 ;
  lon = 36 ;
  pres = 15 ;
  time = 4 ;
variables:
  float xwind(time,pres,lat,lon) ;
    xwind:long_name = "zonal wind" ;
    xwind:units = "m/s" ;
  float lon(lon) ;
    lon:long_name = "longitude" ;
    lon:units = "degrees_east" ;
  float lat(lat) ;
    lat:long_name = "latitude" ;
    lat:units = "degrees_north" ;
  float pres(pres) ;
    pres:long_name = "pressure" ;
    pres:units = "hPa" ;
  double time(time) ;
    time:long_name = "time" ;
    time:units = "days since 1990-1-1 0:0:0" ;
      </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
      <varname>xwind(n,k,j,i)</varname> is associated with the coordinate values <varname>lon(i)</varname>, <varname>lat(j)</varname>, <varname>pres(k)</varname>, and <varname>time(n)</varname>.
    </para>
  </section>
	
  <section>
    <title>Two-Dimensional Latitude, Longitude, Coordinate Variables</title>
    <para>
      The latitude and longitude coordinates of a horizontal grid that was
      not defined as a Cartesian product of latitude and longitude axes,
      can sometimes be represented using two-dimensional coordinate variables.
      These variables are identified as coordinates by use of
      the <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Two-dimensional coordinate variables</title>
      <programlisting>
dimensions:
  xc = 128 ;
  yc = 64 ;
  lev = 18 ;
variables:
  float T(lev,yc,xc) ;
    T:long_name = "temperature" ;
    T:units = "K" ;
    T:coordinates = "lon lat" ;
  float xc(xc) ;
    xc:axis = "X" ;
    xc:long_name = "x-coordinate in Cartesian system" ;
    xc:units = "m" ;
  float yc(yc) ;
    yc:axis = "Y" ;
    yc:long_name = "y-coordinate in Cartesian system" ;
    yc:units = "m" ;
  float lev(lev) ;
    lev:long_name = "pressure level" ;
    lev:units = "hPa" ;
  float lon(yc,xc) ;
    lon:long_name = "longitude" ;
    lon:units = "degrees_east" ;
  float lat(yc,xc) ;
    lat:long_name = "latitude" ;
    lat:units = "degrees_north" ;
      </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
      <varname>T(k,j,i)</varname> is associated with the coordinate
      values <varname>lon(j,i)</varname>, <varname>lat(j,i)</varname>,
      and <varname>lev(k)</varname>. The vertical coordinate is represented
      by the coordinate variable <varname>lev(lev)</varname> and the
      latitude and longitude coordinates are represented by the auxiliary
      coordinate variables <varname>lat(yc,xc)</varname> and
      <varname>lon(yc,xc)</varname> which are identified by the
      <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that coordinate variables are also defined for the
      <varname>xc</varname> and <varname>yc</varname> dimensions.
      This faciliates processing of this data by generic applications
      that don't recognize the multidimensional latitude and longitude
      coordinates.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="reduced-horizontal-grid">
    <title>Reduced Horizontal Grid</title>
    <para>
      A "reduced" longitude-latitude grid is one in which the points
      are arranged along constant latitude lines with the number of
      points on a latitude line decreasing toward the poles.
      Storing this type of gridded data in two-dimensional arrays
      wastes space, and results in the presence of missing values
      in the 2D coordinate variables. We recommend that this type
      of gridded data be stored using the compression scheme
      described in <xref linkend="compression-by-gathering"/>.
      Compression by gathering preserves structure by storing
      a set of indices that allows an application to easily
      scatter the compressed data back to two-dimensional
      arrays. The compressed latitude and longitude auxiliary
      coordinate variables are identified by
      the <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Reduced horizontal grid</title>
      <programlisting>
dimensions:
  londim = 128 ;
  latdim = 64 ;
  rgrid = 6144 ;
variables:
  float PS(rgrid) ;
    PS:long_name = "surface pressure" ;
    PS:units = "Pa" ;
    PS:coordinates = "lon lat" ;
  float lon(rgrid) ;
    lon:long_name = "longitude" ;
    lon:units = "degrees_east" ;
  float lat(rgrid) ;
    lat:long_name = "latitude" ;
    lat:units = "degrees_north" ;
  int rgrid(rgrid);
    rgrid:compress = "latdim londim";
      </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
      <varname>PS(n)</varname> is associated with the coordinate
      values <varname>lon(n)</varname>, <varname>lat(n)</varname>.
      Compressed grid index <varname>(n)</varname> would be assigned
      to 2D index <varname>(j,i)</varname> (C index conventions) where
      <programlisting>
j = rgrid(n) / 128
i = rgrid(n) - 128*j
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      Notice that even if an application does not recognize
      the <varname>compress</varname> attribute, the grids
      stored in this format can still be handled, by an application
      that recognizes the <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><emphasis role="deletedtext">Timeseries of Station Data</emphasis></title>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="commenttext">This section has been superseded by the
      treatment of time series as a type of discrete sampling geometry in
      Chapter 9.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para><emphasis role="deletedtext">
      To represent data at scattered points it is convenient to use a variable with one dimension to represent the measurement locations. Auxiliary coordinate variables are used to associate a single spatial dimension with multiple independent coordinates.
    </emphasis></para>
    <example>
      <title><emphasis role="deletedtext">Timeseries of station data</emphasis></title>
      <programlisting><emphasis role="deletedtext">
dimensions:
  station = 10 ;  // measurement locations
  pressure = 11 ; // pressure levels
  time = UNLIMITED ;
variables:
  float humidity(time,pressure,station) ;
    humidity:long_name = "specific humidity" ;
    humidity:coordinates = "lat lon" ;
  double time(time) ;
    time:long_name = "time of measurement" ;
    time:units = "days since 1970-01-01 00:00:00" ;
  float lon(station) ;
    lon:long_name = "station longitude";
    lon:units = "degrees_east";
  float lat(station) ;
    lat:long_name = "station latitude" ;
    lat:units = "degrees_north" ;
  float pressure(pressure) ;
    pressure:long_name = "pressure" ;
    pressure:units = "hPa" ;
      </emphasis></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para><emphasis role="deletedtext">
      <varname>humidity(n,k,i)</varname> is associated with the coordinate values <varname>time(n)</varname>, <varname>pressure(k)</varname>, <varname>lat(i)</varname>, and <varname>lon(i)</varname>.
    </emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title><emphasis role="deletedtext">Trajectories</emphasis></title>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="commenttext">This section has been superseded by the
      treatment of trajectories as a type of discrete sampling geometry in
      Chapter 9.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para><emphasis role="deletedtext">
      A possible representation of the spatiotemporal locations of
      measurements along a flight path is to use time to parameterize
      the trajectory and use auxiliary coordinate variables to provide
      the spatial locations.
    </emphasis></para>
    <example>
      <title><emphasis role="deletedtext">Trajectories</emphasis></title>
      <programlisting><emphasis role="deletedtext">
dimensions:
  time = 1000 ;
variables:
  float O3(time) ;
    O3:long_name = "ozone concentration" ;
    O3:units = "1e-9" ;
    O3:coordinates = "lon lat z" ;
  double time(time) ;
    time:long_name = "time" ;
    time:units = "days since 1970-01-01 00:00:00" ;
  float lon(time) ;
    lon:long_name = "longitude" ;
    lon:units = "degrees_east" ;
  float lat(time) ;
    lat:long_name = "latitude" ;
    lat:units = "degrees_north" ;
  float z(time) ;
    z:long_name = "height above mean sea level" ;
    z:units = "km" ;
    z:positive = "up" ;
      </emphasis></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para><emphasis role="deletedtext">
      <varname>O3(n)</varname> is associated with the coordinate
      values <varname>time(n)</varname>, <varname>z(n)</varname>,
      <varname>lat(n)</varname>, and <varname>lon(n)</varname>.
    </emphasis></para>
  </section>

  <section id="grid-mappings-and-projections">
    <title><emphasis role="deletedtext">Grid Mappings and Projections</emphasis><emphasis role="newtext">Horizontal Coordinate Reference Systems, Grid Mappings, and Projections</emphasis></title>
    <para>
      When the coordinate variables for a horizontal grid are not longitude
      and latitude, it is required that the true latitude and longitude
      coordinates be supplied via the <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute.
      If in addition it is desired to describe the mapping between the
      given coordinate variables and the true latitude and longitude
      coordinates, the attribute <varname>grid_mapping</varname> may be
      used to supply this description. This attribute is attached to data
      variables so that variables with different mappings may be present
      in a single file. The attribute takes a string value which is the
      name of another variable in the file that provides the description
      of the mapping via a collection of attached attributes. This variable
      is called <emphasis>a grid mapping variable</emphasis> and is of
      arbitrary type since it contains no data. Its purpose is to act as
      a container for the attributes that define the mapping. The one
      attribute that all grid mapping variables must have is
      <varname>grid_mapping_name</varname> which takes a string value that
      contains the mapping's name. The other attributes that define a
      specific mapping depend on the value of
      <varname>grid_mapping_name</varname>. The valid values of
      <varname>grid_mapping_name</varname> along with the attributes
      that provide specific map parameter values are
      described in <xref linkend="appendix-grid-mappings"/>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
        <emphasis role="newtext">When the coordinate variables for a horizontal grid are longitude
        and latitude, a grid mapping variable with <varname>grid_mapping_name</varname>
        of <varname>latitude_longitude</varname> may be used to specify the 
        ellipsoid and prime meridian.</emphasis>
    </para>
    
    <para>
        In order to make use of a grid mapping to directly calculate latitude
        and longitude values it is necessary to associate the coordinate
        variables with the independent variables of the mapping.
        This is done by assigning a <varname>standard_name</varname> to
        the coordinate variable. The appropriate values of the
        <varname>standard_name</varname> depend on the grid mapping and
        are given in <xref linkend="appendix-grid-mappings"/>.
    </para>
    
    <example>
      <title>Rotated pole grid</title>
      <programlisting>
dimensions:
  rlon = 128 ;
  rlat = 64 ;
  lev = 18 ;
variables:
  float T(lev,rlat,rlon) ;
    T:long_name = "temperature" ;
    T:units = "K" ;
    T:coordinates = "lon lat" ;
    T:grid_mapping = "rotated_pole" ;
  char rotated_pole
    rotated_pole:grid_mapping_name = "rotated_latitude_longitude" ;
    rotated_pole:grid_north_pole_latitude = 32.5 ;
    rotated_pole:grid_north_pole_longitude = 170. ;
  float rlon(rlon) ;
    rlon:long_name = "longitude in rotated pole grid" ;
    rlon:units = "degrees" ;
    rlon:standard_name = "grid_longitude";
  float rlat(rlat) ;
    rlat:long_name = "latitude in rotated pole grid" ;
    rlat:units = "degrees" ;
    rlon:standard_name = "grid_latitude";
  float lev(lev) ;
    lev:long_name = "pressure level" ;
    lev:units = "hPa" ;
  float lon(rlat,rlon) ;
    lon:long_name = "longitude" ;
    lon:units = "degrees_east" ;
  float lat(rlat,rlon) ;
    lat:long_name = "latitude" ;
    lat:units = "degrees_north" ;
      </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
      A CF compliant application can determine that rlon and rlat are
      longitude and latitude values in the rotated grid by
      recognizing the standard names <varname>grid_longitude</varname>
      and <varname>grid_latitude</varname>. Note that the units
      of the rotated longitude and latitude axes are given as
      <varname>degrees</varname>. This should prevent a COARDS
      compliant application from mistaking the variables
      <varname>rlon</varname> and <varname>rlat</varname> to be
      actual longitude and latitude coordinates. The entries for these
      names in the standard name table indicate the appropriate sign
      conventions for the units of <varname>degrees</varname>.
    </para>
    
    <example id="lambert-conformal-projection">
      <title>Lambert conformal projection</title>
      <programlisting>
dimensions:
  y = 228;
  x = 306;
  time = 41;

variables:
  int Lambert_Conformal;
    Lambert_Conformal:grid_mapping_name = "lambert_conformal_conic";
    Lambert_Conformal:standard_parallel = 25.0;
    Lambert_Conformal:longitude_of_central_meridian = 265.0;
    Lambert_Conformal:latitude_of_projection_origin = 25.0;
  double y(y);
    y:units = "km";
    y:long_name = "y coordinate of projection";
    y:standard_name = "projection_y_coordinate";
  double x(x);
    x:units = "km";
    x:long_name = "x coordinate of projection";
    x:standard_name = "projection_x_coordinate";
  double lat(y, x);
    lat:units = "degrees_north";
    lat:long_name = "latitude coordinate";
    lat:standard_name = "latitude";
  double lon(y, x);
    lon:units = "degrees_east";
    lon:long_name = "longitude coordinate";
    lon:standard_name = "longitude";
  int time(time);
    time:long_name = "forecast time";
    time:units = "hours since 2004-06-23T22:00:00Z";
  float Temperature(time, y, x);
    Temperature:units = "K";
    Temperature:long_name = "Temperature @ surface";
    Temperature:missing_value = 9999.0;
    Temperature:coordinates = "lat lon";
    Temperature:grid_mapping = "Lambert_Conformal";
      </programlisting>

    <para>
      An application can determine that <varname>x</varname> and
      <varname>y</varname> are the projection coordinates by
      recognizing the standard names <varname>projection_x_coordinate</varname>
      and <varname>projection_y_coordinate</varname>. The grid mapping
      variable <varname>Lambert_Conformal</varname> contains the mapping
      parameters as attributes, and is associated with
      the <varname>Temperature</varname> variable via its
      <varname>grid_mapping attribute</varname>.
    </para>
    
    </example>

    <example id="latitude-and-longitude-on-a-spherical-earth">
      <title><emphasis role="newtext">Latitude and longitude on a spherical Earth</emphasis></title>
      <programlisting>
<emphasis role="newtext">dimensions:
  lat = 18 ;
  lon = 36 ;
variables:
  double lat(lat) ;
  double lon(lon) ;
  float temp(lat, lon) ;
    temp:long_name = "temperature" ;
    temp:units = "K" ;
    temp:grid_mapping = "crs" ;
  int crs ;
    crs:grid_mapping_name = "latitude_longitude"
    crs:semi_major_axis = 6371000.0 ;
    crs:inverse_flattening = 0 ;</emphasis>
      </programlisting>
    </example>

    <example id="latitude-and-longitude-on-the-wgs-1984-datum">
      <title><emphasis role="newtext">Latitude and longitude on the WGS 1984 datum</emphasis></title>
      <programlisting>
<emphasis role="newtext">dimensions:
  lat = 18 ;
  lon = 36 ;
variables:
  double lat(lat) ;
  double lon(lon) ;
  float temp(lat, lon) ;
    temp:long_name = "temperature" ;
    temp:units = "K" ;
    temp:grid_mapping = "crs" ;
  int crs ;
    crs:grid_mapping_name = "latitude_longitude";
    crs:longitude_of_prime_meridian = 0.0 ;
    crs:semi_major_axis = 6378137.0 ;
    crs:inverse_flattening = 298.257223563 ;</emphasis>
      </programlisting>
    </example>

    <example id="british-national-grid">
      <title><emphasis role="newtext">British National Grid</emphasis></title>
      <programlisting>
<emphasis role="newtext">dimensions:
  lat = 648 ;
  lon = 648 ;
  y = 18 ;
  x = 36 ;
variables:
  double x(x) ;
    x:standard_name = "projection_x_coordinate" ;
    x:units = "m" ;
  double y(y) ;
    y:standard_name = "projection_y_coordinate" ;
    y:units = "m" ;
  double lat(y, x) ;
  double lon(y, x) ;
  float temp(y, x) ;
    temp:long_name = "temperature" ;
    temp:units = "K" ;
    temp:coordinates = "lat lon" ;
    temp:grid_mapping = "crs" ;
  int crs ;
    crs:grid_mapping_name = "transverse_mercator";
    crs:semi_major_axis = 6377563.396 ;
    crs:semi_minor_axis = 6356256.910 ;
    crs:inverse_flattening = 299.3249646 ;
    crs:latitude_of_projection_origin = 49.0 ;
    crs:longitude_of_projection_origin = -2.0 ;
    crs:false_easting = 400000.0 ;
    crs:false_northing = -100000.0 ;
    crs:scale_factor_at_projection_origin = 0.9996012717 ;</emphasis>
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section id="scalar-coordinate-variables">
    <title>Scalar Coordinate Variables</title>
    <para>
      When a variable has an associated coordinate which is
      single-valued, that coordinate may be represented as a
      scalar variable. Since there is no associated dimension
      these scalar coordinate variables should be attached to
      a data variable via the <varname>coordinates</varname> attribute.
    </para>
    <para>
        Under COARDS the method of providing a single valued coordinate was
        to add a dimension of size one to the variable, and supply the
        corresponding coordinate variable. The new scalar coordinate
        variable is a convenience feature which avoids adding size
        one dimensions to variables. Scalar coordinate variables have
        the same information content and can be used in the same
        contexts as a size one coordinate variable. Note however that
        use of this feature with a latitude, longitude, vertical,
        or time coordinate will inhibit COARDS conforming
        applications from recognizing them.
    </para>
    <para>
        Once a name is used for a scalar coordinate variable it can not
        be used for a 1D coordinate variable. For this reason we
        strongly recommend against using a name for a scalar coordinate
        variable that matches the name of any dimension in the file.
    </para>
    <example id="multiple-forecasts-from-single-analysis">
      <title>Multiple forecasts from a single analysis</title>
      <programlisting>
dimensions:
  lat = 180 ;
  lon = 360 ;
  time = UNLIMITED ;
variables:
  double atime
    atime:standard_name = "forecast_reference_time" ;
    atime:units = "hours since 1999-01-01 00:00" ;
  double time(time);
    time:standard_name = "time" ;
    time:units = "hours since 1999-01-01 00:00" ;
  double lon(lon) ;
    lon:long_name = "station longitude";
    lon:units = "degrees_east";
  double lat(lat) ;
    lat:long_name = "station latitude" ;
    lat:units = "degrees_north" ;
  double p500
    p500:long_name = "pressure" ;
    p500:units = "hPa" ;
    p500:positive = "down" ;
  float height(time,lat,lon);
    height:long_name = "geopotential height" ;
    height:standard_name = "geopotential_height" ;
    height:units = "m" ;
    height:coordinates = "atime p500" ;
data:
  time = 6., 12., 18., 24. ;
  atime = 0. ;
  p500 = 500. ;
      </programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
      In this example both the analysis time and the single pressure level are represented using scalar coordinate variables. The analysis time is identified by the standard name "forecast_reference_time" while the valid time of the forecast is identified by the standard name "time".
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>





