<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
	<title>
		Reduction of Dataset Size
	</title>

	<para>
		There are two methods for reducing dataset size: packing
		and compression. By packing we mean altering the data
		in a way that reduces its precision. By compression we
		mean techniques that store the data more efficiently
		and result in no precision loss. Compression only
		works in certain circumstances, e.g., when a variable
		contains a significant amount of missing or repeated
		data values. In this case it is possible to make use of
		standard utilities, e.g., UNIX <computeroutput>compress</computeroutput> 
		or GNU <computeroutput>gzip</computeroutput>, to
		compress the entire file after it has been written. In
		this section we offer an alternative compression method
		that is applied on a variable by variable basis. This
		has the advantage that only one variable need be
		uncompressed at a given time. The disadvantage is that
		generic utilities that don't recognize the CF conventions
		will not be able to operate on compressed variables.
	</para>

	<section id="packed-data">
		<title>Packed Data</title>
		<para>
			At the current time the netCDF interface does
			not provide for packing data. However a simple
			packing may be achieved through the use of the
			optional NUG defined attributes 
			<varname>scale_factor</varname>
			and
			<varname>add_offset</varname>. 
			After the data values of a variable
			have been read, they are to be multiplied by
			the 
			<varname>scale_factor</varname>, and have 
			<varname>add_offset</varname> 
			added to
			them. If both attributes are present, the data
			are scaled before the offset is added. When
			scaled data are written, the application should
			first subtract the offset and then divide by the
			scale factor. The units of a variable should be
			representative of the unpacked data.
		</para>
		<para>
			This standard is more restrictive than the NUG
			with respect to the use of the 
			<varname>scale_factor</varname> and
			<varname>add_offset</varname> 
			attributes; ambiguities and precision
			problems related to data type conversions
			are resolved by these restrictions. If the
			<varname>scale_factor</varname> 
			and 
			<varname>add_offset</varname> 
			attributes are of
			the same data type as the associated variable,
			the unpacked data is assumed to be of the
			same data type as the packed data. However,
			if the 
			<varname>scale_factor</varname> 
			and 
			<varname>add_offset</varname> 
			attributes
			are of a different data type from the variable
			(containing the packed data) then the unpacked
			data should match the type of these attributes,
			which must both be of type <varname>float</varname> or both be of
			type <varname>double</varname>. An additional restriction in this
			case is that the variable containing the packed
			data must be of type <varname>byte</varname>, <varname>short</varname> or <varname>int</varname>. It is
			not advised to unpack an <varname>int</varname> into a <varname>float</varname> as
			there is a potential precision loss.
		</para>
		<para>
			When data to be packed contains missing values
			the attributes that indicate missing values
			(<varname>_FillValue</varname>, <varname>valid_min</varname>, <varname>valid_max</varname>, <varname>valid_range</varname>)
			must be of the same data type as the packed
			data. See <xref linkend="missing-data"/> for a discussion of how
			applications should treat variables that have
			attributes indicating both missing values and
			transformations defined by a scale and/or offset.
		</para>
	</section>



	<section id="compression-by-gathering">
		<title>Compression by Gathering</title>
		<para>
			To save space in the netCDF file, it may be
			desirable to eliminate points from data arrays
			that are invariably missing. Such a compression
			can operate over one or more adjacent axes, and
			is accomplished with reference to a list of the
			points to be stored. The list is constructed by
			considering a mask array that only includes the
			axes to be compressed, and then mapping this array
			onto one dimension without reordering. The list is
			the set of indices in this one-dimensional mask
			of the required points. In the compressed array,
			the axes to be compressed are all replaced by a
			single axis, whose dimension is the number of
			wanted points. The wanted points appear along
			this dimension in the same order they appear in
			the uncompressed array, with the unwanted points
			skipped over. Compression and uncompression are
			executed by looping over the list.
		</para>
		<para>
			The list is stored as the coordinate variable
			for the compressed axis of the data array. Thus,
			the list variable and its dimension have the same
			name. The list variable has a string attribute
			<varname>compress</varname>, <emphasis>containing a blank-separated list
			of the dimensions which were affected by the
			compression in the order of the CDL declaration
			of the uncompressed array</emphasis>. The presence of
			this attribute identifies the list variable
			as such. The list, the original dimensions
			and coordinate variables (including boundary
			variables), and the compressed variables with
			all the attributes of the uncompressed variables
			are written to the netCDF file. The uncompressed
			variables can be reconstituted exactly as they
			were using this information.
		</para>
		<para>
			<example>
				<title>Horizontal compression of a three-dimensional array</title>
				<para>
					 We eliminate sea
					 points at all depths in a
					 longitude-latitude-depth array of
					 soil temperatures. In this case,
					 only the longitude and latitude
					 axes would be affected by the
					 compression. We construct a list
					 <varname>landpoint(landpoint)</varname> containing
					 the indices of land points.
				</para>
				<para>
					<programlisting>
dimensions:
  lat=73;
  lon=96;
  landpoint=2381;
  depth=4;
variables:
  int landpoint(landpoint);
    landpoint:compress="lat lon";
  float landsoilt(depth,landpoint);
    landsoilt:long_name="soil temperature";
    landsoilt:units="K";
  float depth(depth);
  float lat(lat);
  float lon(lon);
data:
  landpoint=363, 364, 365, ...;

					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					Since 
					<computeroutput>landpoint(0)=363</computeroutput>, 
					for instance, we know that 
					<computeroutput>landsoilt(*,0)</computeroutput> 
					maps on to point 363 of the original data with dimensions 
					<computeroutput>(lat,lon)</computeroutput>. 
					This corresponds to indices 
					<computeroutput>(3,75)</computeroutput>, 
					i.e., 
					<computeroutput>363 = 3*96 + 75</computeroutput>. 
				</para>
			</example>
		</para>
		<para>
			<example>
				<title>Compression of a three-dimensional field</title>
				<para>
					We compress a longitude-latitude-depth field of ocean salinity by eliminating points below the sea-floor. In this case, all three dimensions are affected by the compression, since there are successively fewer active ocean points at increasing depths.
				</para>
				<para>
					<programlisting>
variables:
  float salinity(time,oceanpoint);
  int oceanpoint(oceanpoint);
    oceanpoint:compress="depth lat lon";
  float depth(depth);
  float lat(lat);
  float lon(lon);
  double time(time);
					</programlisting>
				</para>
				<para>
					This information implies that
					the salinity field should be
					uncompressed to an array with
					dimensions 
					<computeroutput>(depth,lat,lon)</computeroutput>.
				</para>
			</example>
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>







